<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nordegraf.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://nordegraf.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-09T17:30:58+00:00</updated><id>https://nordegraf.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nordegraf’s Blog</title><subtitle>Nordegraf's Personal Blog</subtitle><author><name>Niklas Conen</name></author><entry><title type="html">New website for the CF-Selbsthilfe Frankfurt e.V.</title><link href="https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/10/30/new-website-for-cf-selbsthilfe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New website for the CF-Selbsthilfe Frankfurt e.V." /><published>2022-10-30T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-30T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/10/30/new-website-for-cf-selbsthilfe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/10/30/new-website-for-cf-selbsthilfe.html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago the CF-Selbsthilfe Frankfurt e.V. reached out to me for help with their website. They are a non-profit organization that supports people with cystic fibrosis and their families in Frankfurt and the surrounding area, including my family when I was diagnosed. Naturally I offered to help them without hesitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to announce, that their new site is now live here: &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://www.cf-selbsthilfe.de/&quot;&gt;cf-selbsthilfe.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their page is built similarly to this blog. Jekyll and Bootstrap are used for a responsive layout and the final page is hosted on GitHub Pages. But this time the task of hosting this site was a bit more intricate. Posts are split into events and actual posts using categories. Both are listed on seperate pages and need pagination, which the jekyll-paginate plugin can not provide. To be able to use the jekyll-paginate-v2 plugin, which solves most of these problems, the page needs to be built using a &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/CF-Selbsthilfe/cf-selbsthilfe.de/blob/main/.github/workflows/jekyll.yml&quot;&gt;GitHub Actions workflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several actions to built Jekyll pages already exist and all of them have different benefits or disadvantages. I chose &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/limjh16/jekyll-action-ts&quot;&gt;jekyll-action-ts&lt;/a&gt; because it uses node.js instead of a docker container and automatically formats the code using &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://prettier.io&quot;&gt;prettier.io&lt;/a&gt;. To keep the list of upcoming events up-to-date the page is rebuild once a week using a cron job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events are displayed in a calendar, which is built using &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://fullcalendar.io&quot;&gt;FullCalendar&lt;/a&gt;. For that a &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/CF-Selbsthilfe/cf-selbsthilfe.de/blob/main/_pages/events.html&quot;&gt;JSON file&lt;/a&gt; is generated formating all necessary data to be able to display the events in the calendar. Additionally FullCalendar can display events loaded from a Google Calendar or from iCalendar files, but beacause of privacy concerns I decided against that for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use the associations top-level domain without publishing my blog on their domain I had to move the code repository to its own &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/CF-Selbsthilfe&quot;&gt;GitHub Organization&lt;/a&gt;. The code is open sourced under the GNU GPLv3 license and is accessible through its &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/CF-Selbsthilfe/cf-selbsthilfe.de&quot;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole project took me about two weeks and I’m really happy with the result!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Niklas Conen</name></author><category term="cf-selbsthilfe" /><category term="cystic-fibrosis" /><summary type="html">A few weeks ago the CF-Selbsthilfe Frankfurt e.V. reached out to me for help with their website. They are a non-profit organization that supports people with cystic fibrosis and their families in Frankfurt and the surrounding area, including my family when I was diagnosed. Naturally I offered to help them without hesitation. I’m happy to announce, that their new site is now live here: cf-selbsthilfe.de.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking into how the game Spiral Knights is built</title><link href="https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/07/20/spiral-knights-dat-to-xml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking into how the game Spiral Knights is built" /><published>2022-07-20T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-20T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/07/20/spiral-knights-dat-to-xml</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nordegraf.github.io//2022/07/20/spiral-knights-dat-to-xml.html">&lt;p&gt;More than 10 years ago in 2012 I stumbled upon a game called Spiral Knights in the Free-to-Play section of the Steam Store.
The beautiful neon-like color scheme, cute artstyle and lovely story got me hooked quite fast. And so Spiral Knights became the second MMO I played a bit more extensively after Lego Universe closed its gates the same year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developed by Three Rings Design and published by SEGA Spiral Knights is a quite grind heavy Top-Down Hack and Slash type game which sends you on a quest through an ever changing set of gradually more difficult missions in the so called Clockworks on the planet Cradle… Well at least the advertising says that. While definitely being quite diverse the actual reality is that the same missions are rotated on a daily or weekly basis depending on the mission type. At some point specific routes through the clockwork revealed themselves as the most efficient for getting crafting materials resulting in me grinding only these ones for hours. I still enjoyed my time on Cradle and I have been revisiting the game ever so often over the past 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly the game got less popular over time to a point were today the games servers are mostly empty. Moreover Three Rings Design dissolved in 2016 and a new company called Grey Havens consisting of old Three Rings employees formed to keep some of their games alive. By now only Spiral Knights and Puzzle Pirates are kept on life support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being interested in how games work behind the curtain I set out to look into Spiral Knights game files to see what I’m able to understand. I’ll summarize my findings a bit below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 Three Rings launched a website called gamegardens.com and wiki.gamegardens.com as a plattform for making games using their developed Java libraries. Sadly the website is gone, but some captures are availabe on the WaybackMachine. For gamegardens ThreeRings published their libraries publicly on GitHub. Their core libraries are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/threerings/narya&quot;&gt;Narya&lt;/a&gt; (mainly for networking)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/threerings/nenya&quot;&gt;Nenya&lt;/a&gt; (mainly for media management)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/threerings/vilya&quot;&gt;Vilya&lt;/a&gt; (some frameworks for specific game types)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/threerings/clyde&quot;&gt;Clyde&lt;/a&gt; (various utility)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/threerings/getdown&quot;&gt;getdown&lt;/a&gt; (downloading and updating)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(They must be huge Tolkien fans)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover a core library they used is &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://legacy.lwjgl.org&quot;&gt;LWJGL2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more libraries in the games folders, but the ones listed above are probably the most important ones.
In the code subdirectory of the games main files is a library called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;projectx-pcode.jar&lt;/code&gt;. My best guess is, that most of the games core functionality is build upon the libraries in this .jar, which includes code of their open source libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clyde includes utility for importing and converting the games .dat binary files to a human readable .xml format. As a first step I set out to use this utility for converting the games .dat files to .xml. In Clyde the import and export is done using the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;com.threerings.export.BinaryImport&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;com.threerings.export.XMLExport&lt;/code&gt; classes. In the games file these libraries are contained in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;com.threerings.export.b&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;com.threerings.export.aA&lt;/code&gt; .class files. Using a bash script I installed the games &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;projectx-pcode.jar&lt;/code&gt; into a local maven repository making its source code available for usage. Then I simply wrote a small app searching the games directory for .dat files and then converting all of them to .xml. The apps code is available on my &lt;a class=&quot;link&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/Nordegraf/SKdatToXML&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; including the bash script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The converted files contain a lot of information about missions, items, worlds, models, etc. and mostly reference configuration classes also contained in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;projectx-pcode.jar&lt;/code&gt;. A nice small project would be a page listing all of the games missions or items or similar, but for now I’ll leave this as is.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Niklas Conen</name></author><category term="spiral_knights" /><category term="spiral_knights" /><summary type="html">More than 10 years ago in 2012 I stumbled upon a game called Spiral Knights in the Free-to-Play section of the Steam Store. The beautiful neon-like color scheme, cute artstyle and lovely story got me hooked quite fast. And so Spiral Knights became the second MMO I played a bit more extensively after Lego Universe closed its gates the same year.</summary></entry></feed>